Doug Baron

1210 Olympus Dr, Austin, TX 78733 dbaron.chilehead.com 512-577-4775 http://www.linkedin.com/in/dougbaron

Summary

- Senior Software Developer fluent in Java, Javascript and Internet technologies from TCP/IP, HTTP, CSS and HTML to Spring, Struts, SOAP, REST, JSON, XML, Xschema and XSLT
- Mobile domain development with iOS, Objective C and Xcode
- Keen interest in architecture and team leadership
- 15+ years of Software development experience using various flavors of UNIX
- 10+ years of Java development with Spring MVC, Hibernate and Oracle SQL

Technical Skills

Languages and Protocols: Java, SQL, J2EE / Swing, Objective C, JavaScript, C / C++, Python, PHP, XML, XSchema, XSL, SOAP, WSDL, REST, XML-RPC, HTML, CSS, JSON, HTTP, SQL, TCP/IP, IPv6.

Web Tools: Struts, Tiles, FreeMarker, Velocity, JSP, Taglib, Spring. **Frameworks and Services**: Apache, DropWizard, Tomcat, Glassfish, WebLogic, JBoss, Hibernate, Drools, Castor, Oracle, HSQLDB, MySQL, Drupal, Lucene, JasperReports, Maven, Ant, Subversion, Git, Perforce, JIRA, Confluence. **Certifications**: Sun Certified Programmer for Java Platform, SE 6; Oracle Database SQL Expert; PMP Pending.

Professional History

Ambonare Nov 2014 – Sep 2015

Senior Software Engineer

Lead Developer on Texas Railroad Commission IT Modernization Program development team.

- Primary contributor to design, planning, development and delivery of useranticipated service to file and track permit exception applications.
- Worked with business analysts to translate requirements into use cases and detailed designs.

Stack: Java J2EE, PrimeFaces, WebLogic 10g, JavaScript, Eclipse, Oracle 10.x, JasperReports, Git, Jenkins, JIRA, Stash, SourceTree.

Bridge360 Aug 2012 – Sep 2014

Software Engineer

Assured quality of feature-rich Internet gateway device with worldwide audience.

- Created and executed manual and automated tests in a complex networking environment to validate features and performance.
- Wrote multi-threaded Java service to generate gateway traffic emulating over 10 million devices, published to a JMS message queue (RabbitMQ), for load testing. Provided admin GUI using DropWizard, Freemarker, Backbone.js and iQuery.
- Improved communication capabilities of automated test reporting system with new XSL feature acting on log file markup.
- Used JIRA for bug tracking, issue tracking and project management.

For financial services client, extended and maintained 3-tier Java payment card processing service and web applications used by the U.S. Treasury.

- Used advanced Oracle database SQL queries and PL-SQL packages in support of government electronic benefit payments.
- Wrote and debugged Drools rules framework for ACH processor business logic.
- Debugged and extended report generation with iReports and JasperReports.
- Team used Scrum-based agile workflow with sprints and daily stand-up meetings.

Stack: **Java** J2SE, J2EE, JDK 1.6, 1.7 with Eclipse 4.x, JUnit and E2asyMock, Python, JavaScript, JQuery, JSON, JSP, Struts, Tomcat, RTC/Jazz, Maven, Jenkins, Oracle Virtualbox, ApTest, JIRA, Confluence, SOAP, WSDL, Scapy, Wireshark, Oracle 10.x, Ubuntu Linux, XHTML, CSS, XML, XSL, XSLT, RabbitMQ.

Rêv Worldwide / MPower Mobile Senior Software Engineer

May 2010 - April 2012

- Developed Java web service supporting mobile clients of the <u>RêvCOIN</u> credit card acceptance / Point of Sale solution. Also included a REST service for remote client access.
- Developed iPhone client application for the <u>RêvCOIN</u> mobile Point of Sale solution. App could enroll new users, accept credit card payments, show history and issue refunds.

Stack: Java J2EE, Spring MVC, Log4j, Eclipse, Oracle, Hibernate, JBoss, Linux.

Blue Coat Systems [acquired Permeo, June 2006] Senior Software Engineer

June 2006 – April 2010

Designed sophisticated upgrades to Java applet-based administration application in support of new network appliance features.

- Designed and implemented Swing-based outline editor to manage user-group / url-category web access rules, using in-line table editing.
- Wrote highly reusable foundation for tabular data display with support for column set selection, value filtering and sorting.
- Supported client update automation with a Python-based database upgrader and scheduler.

Stack: Java J2EE, Swing, Python, Perforce, Eclipse, Oracle 6.x, Code Collaborator, Centos Linux.

Developed administration application for policy-based network security / connectivity appliance.

- Extended velocity library to rapidly generate form pages with extensive use of DHTML for usability.
- Dramatically improved configuration speed by replacing repeated page visits with a custom JavaScript-based table builder with in-place cell editing.
- Designed presentation for license overloading feature, offering advanced information and control while preserving the panel's original simplicity.
- Developed interface to configure and monitor service high availability.

Stack: Java J2EE, LinuxHA, JavaScript, Subversion, Eclipse, Struts, Tiles, Velocity, CSS, Lucene, Fedora Linux.

Earlier Projects

Independent Consultant

August 2003 - August 2004

dba Chilehead Software

- Cirrus Logic:
 - Selected Tomcat/Struts/Tiles/JSP/TagLib infrasture, developed Web application extending a proprietary XML CMS.
 - o Wrote XSL transformations for product catalogue publishing.
 - Authored build system based on Ant and CVS, emulating Documentum content versioning.
- IBM Research:
 - Worked on infrastructure for new features of the <u>IBM PartnerWorld</u> website.
 - Created XML-based content workflow using Ant, XSL and other tools.
- **Gridiron Recruits**: Designed and implemented a Web-based, standalone CD data retrieval system for <u>football recruiting</u>. Highly customized Tomcat configuration developed for read-only service delivery. Recreated in Javascript with Prototype, then jQuery, for demonstration purposes.
- **Congregation Beth-Israel**: Assisted congregational Web site upgrade on a volunteer basis.
- **Animatrix, Inc**: Produced promotional site selling tickets to the premiere of <u>PASSIONADA</u>, a new film directed by Dan Ireland.
- **AquaMinds, Inc:** Developed end-user productivity application prototype.
 - Designed XML media interchange format including formal DTD.
 - Created interactive Java Swing application with tabbed interface whose source is this XML format.
 - o Wrote XSL transformations to and from new XML schema
 - Developed Apple Keynote export module using XSLT.
- Broadband Mechanics: Worked on broadband multimedia application, platform infrastructure and presentation layer:
 - Developed Web-based outlining product using DHTML (JavaScript, DOM API, Events, CSS) and a back end Web service (UserLand Frontier).
 Supports MSIE 5.x and Mozilla, Windows and Macintosh
 - Worked on DreamFactory media aggregation application. Used Python with ZOPE for data storage.

- Implemented Simple Cross-Network Scripting (SNCS), allowing UserTalk function calls to seamlessly invoke web services based on xml-rpc, SOAP or custom protocols.
- Managed the release of Frontier 8.0.5, including: final testing and review; updating the online store; published full and upgrade packages and change notes; supervised beta test group.

Big Chief Partners

July 2000 - March 2001

Consultant / Developer

Designed and developed web services, applications, and project plans for various Internet startup clients.

- Developed web-based administration portal using ASP, VBScript and SQL Server to monitor web traffic and site health for FocusEngine of Israel.
- Administered server deployment, including load balancing scheme based on Alteon Web Systems ACEdirector Web Switch, WebTrends traffic analysis tools, and SiteScope server monitors.
- Created management site for service development and publishing using Cold Fusion and SQL Server for NearSpace of Petaluma, CA. Integrated Cold Fusion with custom Java application for processing XML file uploads.
- Analyzed needs and proposed a solution for Oracle server high availability for Hot Dispatch of Mountain View, CA.

Corio, Inc.

March 1999 – June 2000

Senior Member, Technical Staff

Planned project, prioritized schedule, evaluated tools and services, and developed Java software for ERP service management. Platform included **Java**, **J2EE** (javax.*, JSP, JNDI), and JavaScript and Apache, ATG Dynamo, running on Sun **Solaris** and Microsoft NT.

- Evaluated application servers and recommended ATG Dynamo for internal service development based on features, cost and ease of use.
- Developed security platform EMS (Entitlement Management System) based on SiteMinder, Netscape Directory server (LDAP) and Oracle (JDBC).
- Developed Java APIs and designed management application for enterprisewide security services featuring single sign-on and personalized web pages.
- Integrated with PeopleSoft security APIs to provide EMS services.

Independent Consultant dba Chilehead Software

May 1994 - January 1999

- Animatrix, Inc.: Developed a WYSIWYG Web page layout program in C++ using Metrowerks PowerPlant and DataPak's Paige word processing engine. Implemented AWT-based Java client component for HTML rendering.
- Austin Hayne Corp.: Ported flagship product Employee Appraiser from Windows to Macintosh in Symantec C++ using the TCL application framework.
- Apple Computer, Inc.: Developed system-level emulations libraries for future operating system forward-compatibility project.

 Magic Quest, Inc.: Learned the C++ source base and solved performance problems plaguing Math Ace(r), a CD-ROM-based educational game.
Optimizations yielded an order of magnitude performance gain.

UserLand Software, Inc. Lead Developer

June 1990 - May 1994

Developed <u>UserLand Frontier</u>, a full-featured script development and runtime environment, including compiler construction, database management, outline and word processing, interapplication communications, file system control, thread management, and other OS-level functionality.

- Spearheaded product design, architecture, and development, including feature plans, scheduling, coding, testing and delivery.
- Led the development of versions 2.0 and 3.0, both offering substantial new functionality.
- MacUser Magazine's "Editor's Choice" for Development Tool of the Year.

Living Videotext/Symantec Corp Lead Developer, Engineering Manager

May 1985 - May 1990

Key contributor to MORE 1.0, a powerful outline processor, from feature conception and product design through implementation and final debugging.

- Managed contract programmers. Worked closely with documentation writers.
- Personally responsible for upgrade versions 1.1, 1.1c, and 2.0.
- MORE 1.0 was <u>MacUser Magazine</u>'s Product of the Year and won Best Outliner in <u>MacWorld Magazine</u> Reader's Choice World Class surveys.

Led development of MORE 3.0, a major upgrade with advanced word processing and integrated desktop presentation features.

- Led staff of three full time programmers and two contractors.
- Designed "Rules" feature that applied structured document formatting.
- MORE 3.0 shipped on time and under budget, was hailed as a major step forward in power and ease of use.

Additional Experience

Lake Travis Toastmasters Club Vice President Public Relations, Immediate Past President

2013-2014

Education

Rice University, Houston TX

1979-1983

B.S. Electrical Engineering, B.A. Computer Science